<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://asen4.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://asen4.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-28T03:36:42+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">“Why Politics Makes Us Depressed?” Reflection</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/why-politics-makes-us-depressed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Why Politics Makes Us Depressed?” Reflection"/><published>2023-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/why-politics-makes-us-depressed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/why-politics-makes-us-depressed/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>It’s no secret that listening to politics can make people miserable. Christopher Ojeda, an assistant professor of political science at the University of California, Merced, recently explored this relationship between politics and mental health issues. According to him, an external locus of control brings unhappiness. If someone is directly affected by political action (for instance, having one’s immigration status changed or losing one’s health insurance), their attention will naturally be occupied by events outside her control and lose awareness of the present moment.</p> <p>A recent PLOS One study discovered that politics was a major stressor for millions of Americans during the Trump administration: thanks to politics, people reported they slept less, experienced more stress, anxiety, and depression, and even had more frequent thoughts of suicide with all the systemic changes and policies Trump was pushing forward. Interestingly though, those who experienced the worst mental health effects were consistently amongst the youth population.</p> <p>For a democracy to function, there needs to be engaged and informed citizens — that’s just common sense. But if doing so leads to fatigue and stress and harms one’s relationships, that doesn’t seem like a particularly healthy thing to do. If young people specifically feel they must withdraw from politics to preserve their well-being, we stand to lose the contributions many of them could potentially bring to solving our most pressing problems, like gun violence and climate change. They will inherit this country and planet and all contemporary political issues will fall in their hands eventually — it’s no wonder that the younger generation is facing increased mental health problems as they are burdened with resolving this mess!</p> <p>Despite these alarming signals, there are signs of hope in sight. In fact, some lawmakers are making greater efforts towards listening to young people and integrating their feedback in decision-making so they can see that their actions have tangible political consequences. All in all, those currently in power need to ensure that young people have greater say and more opportunities for political engagement and empowerment in order to leave their mark on the messy field of politics.</p> <p>Listening to this podcast reminded me of an incident that took place many moons ago. One day, I entered an online discussion to do my social studies homework with my friend. Inspired by reading the points in the textbook, he shared with me how former President Trump was putting the country on the right path by getting rid of “the cancerous immigrants.” As an immigrant myself, I initially reacted angrily, recollecting how difficult it was for my family and I to immigrate to the U.S. Before countering in rage, I asked him why he felt this way. He retorted that “many are taking good jobs away from hard-working Americans.” He described how his father was a long-time employee and lost his job recently because the company decided to outsource his father’s job, and how President Trump would bring jobs like his father’s back to the country. I had nothing left to say as his motivations mirrored mine — struggling to find a livelihood in this country. After contemplating on what he said for a while, I learned that it’s always better to listen before making snap judgements. People are rational; if they seem irrational to you, then you don’t have all the details yet and it’s not always about you. This conversation helped me realize that as much as people seem to be one-sided (e.g., anti-immigrant), people tend to have more motivations driving their decision-making, so it’s best to listen to the whole context. Additionally, I learned it’s helpful to listen to people’s perspective without mixing in my own feelings or opinions to truly understand where they are coming from.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/why-politics-makes-us-depressed-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/why-politics-makes-us-depressed-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/why-politics-makes-us-depressed-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/why-politics-makes-us-depressed.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="podcast"/><category term="why-politics-makes-us-depressed"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Standardized Testing for College Readiness” Deliberation Reflection</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/test-optional-policy-reflection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Standardized Testing for College Readiness” Deliberation Reflection"/><published>2023-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/test-optional-policy-reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/test-optional-policy-reflection/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>A few months ago, I was able to attend the “Standardized Testing for College Readiness” deliberation via Zoom on Tuesday, February 28. As most people are already aware, many colleges around the country are removing their mandate for ACT/SAT testing as part of their admission requirements after the COVID-19 pandemic took place, adopting a “test-blind” or “test-optional” style. Although the pandemic has died down today, many colleges are still hanging onto this policy and don’t have any intention of reinstating the requirement again. However, some colleges like MIT have reinstated the requirement this past year because “they are an important factor in assessing the academic preparation of applicants from all backgrounds,” according to their admissions website.</p> <p>Most of the approaches the moderators discussed focused on abolishing the standardized testing requirement and making the admission process emphasize more on personal qualities rather than academic strengths. In the real world, most people are concerned about one’s softer qualities, overall character, skillsets, and ultimately want to know if they can perform their job appropriately — that’s what it boils down to in reality. Sure, these test scores help colleges compare students from different high schools across a normalized setting, especially true when the course rigor varies from school to school depending on the teacher, of course. Even so, it’s a small piece of the puzzle. Someone during the deliberation brought up a valid point where as long as one performs to the minimum expectations, meaning they don’t have a solid 4.0 GPA but have <i>mostly</i> As across all of their courses, it’s sufficient information to suggest they’re an academically-strong student. That information by itself is sufficient to show admissions officers that a particular student will succeed at their college and removes the necessity of having a standardized testing requirement.</p> <p>Interestingly, one of their other approaches involved revising, rather than eliminating, standardized tests. As most people know right now, major changes are coming to the SAT within the next year or so, where the exam will shift to a digital format and shrink to about two hours in length! Unsurprisingly, this isn’t a coincidence by the College Board — a so-called “nonprofit organization” — as fewer people are signing up to take the SAT and, consequently, losing profits. But these changes are still insufficient — instead, changes that alleviate the pressure and stress involved during an already stressful process are absolutely necessary. Most students oftenly think before taking the test they will be “dead” because they don’t have a satisfactory test score and won’t get into their college of dreams and, consequently, won’t be “set” for the rest of their life. However, introducing these changes can go a long way in lowering students’ concerns and worries, taking the form of fewer “trick” questions or the release of more questions that closely mirror the rigor of questions on the actual exam. It may adequately prepare students and they may feel less pressured during the real exam.</p> <p>Most of the points they made during the deliberation were valid, and I ultimately feel their approaches should really be considered by key stakeholders like admission officers and testing agencies. Although the admissions process is growing more competitive with each passing year because of the world’s increasing population, filtering students based on a silly test score is unfair and somewhat discriminatory because it doesn’t provide the whole picture of the applicant — in truth, all it’s doing is making money for organizations like the ACT and SAT, as they continue taking advantage of the college admissions process.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/test-optional-policy-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/test-optional-policy-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/test-optional-policy-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/test-optional-policy.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="act"/><category term="college-board"/><category term="sat"/><category term="standardized-testing"/><category term="test-optional"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Whirlpools: A natural phenomenon that can’t necessarily be predicted!</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/whirlpools/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Whirlpools: A natural phenomenon that can’t necessarily be predicted!"/><published>2023-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/whirlpools</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/whirlpools/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Fast-flowing currents in oceans and rivers constantly change direction. Whirlpools are phenomena that occur when water moving in two different directions comes into contact with one another and interact in a rather unusual way. They can’t continue to travel at the same speed and direction through each other, so they are forced to turn and swirl around each other, often forming a vortex shape. Depending on the volume of water and force of colliding waters, whirlpools can appear in different sizes. Some whirlpools form and disappear over a short period of time, while some water systems keep whirlpools for centuries. The larger and more dangerous whirlpools are called maelstroms, capable of fatally engulfing anyone who comes too close.</p> <p>Many people commonly believe whirlpools are bottomless pits, but that’s not really the case. Experiments have shown that whirlpools often pull objects to the bottom of the sea bed. They may then be moved along the seafloor by ocean currents. If the object can float, it may come back to the surface a long way from where the whirlpool was. As a fun fact, because of the Coriolis effect (i.e., the force of the Earth’s rotation), large whirlpools in the Northern Hemisphere tend to rotate counterclockwise, while whirlpools in the Southern Hemisphere tend to rotate clockwise.</p> <p>Researchers have recorded a bizarre phenomenon in fluid dynamics, which has been theoretically predicted before but never really occurred in nature: they have observed whirlpools swirling in tandem for the first time across the Tasman Sea, where two connected ones are spiraling in opposite directions. Whirlpools almost always head westwards, but by pairing up they can move to the east and travel ten times as fast as a single whirlpool, so they can carry water in unusual directions across the ocean.</p> <p>Lately, there’s been talk surrounding a bizarre, flying “whirlpool” that appears in the night sky above Hawaii in January 2023. Though this necessarily isn’t a whirlpool forming in the water, it’s still a neat sighting that left many awe-stricken and puzzled at the time. It was later figured out that the spiral was related to the SpaceX company’s launch of a new satellite — so much for aliens! SpaceX’s Falcon 9 rocket lifted off from Cape Canaveral on January 18 early in the morning. Ejected its remaining fuel while flying in orbit, sunlight illuminated the spiral of frozen fuel, creating this wondrous pattern above the Pacific Ocean.</p> <p>Whirlpools aren’t as destructive as they are depicted in fiction and sci-fi entertainment movies, such as the whirlpool battle in <i>Pirates of the Caribbean</i>. However, they do pose danger to people and small boats. Most people won’t experience the entrapment of a whirlpool’s force but for many, such as kayakers, it is useful to know how to survive one. Get ready for the big one!</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/whirlpools-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/whirlpools-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/whirlpools-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/whirlpools.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eajAEPvsr9U" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural-phenomena"/><category term="whirlpools"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Food Wastage Deliberation Reflection</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/food-wastage-deliberation-reflection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Food Wastage Deliberation Reflection"/><published>2023-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/food-wastage-deliberation-reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/food-wastage-deliberation-reflection/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>A few weeks ago, I was fortunate enough to attend the deliberation held by Vivaan and his teammates, discussing the importance of food wastage here on campus and how action needs to be taken to refine the food options available. It was titled “Solving the Dining Hall Crisis at Penn State” and held on Thursday, February 23. I believe one of their statistics remarked that we waste nearly 455,000 pounds of food a semester. Spending some of my summers living in India, I saw many starving children begging on the street for a morsel of food from any passers-by, but everyone turned a deaf ear to them. It’s disappointing to see that we are lavishly wasting food here, while some people starve around the world and never receive a proper size meal for themselves. Although Penn State has already implemented various programs and many clubs/organizations revolve around this issue, it’s best to continue educating the student population on the importance of food wastage.</p> <p>Moreover, I believe it’s crucial to refine the food options available here on campus. As someone who has allergies and dietary restrictions, I personally feel that the university fails at providing a diverse set of food selections on a daily basis. For example, there are so many meat-offering dineries available here around campus, but for vegetarians, there’s only a single option — the salad bar. This imbalance between vegetarian and non-vegetarian choices is one of the biggest concerns here on campus. Put yourself in the shoes of a vegetarian for a moment and imagine if a mere salad would be able to get you through lunch and dinner seven days a week. That’s what I thought.</p> <p>Additionally, I agree with another one of their points that focused on some renovation changes. For example, if you were to go to Fresco y Caliente in Redifer Commons and order a burrito, I have also seen them mix and drop food onto other food selections as they are making the order in a rush, creating huge concerns like cross-contamination. This can be the cause of most foodborne infections. They also need to focus on implementing more sanitary guidelines for their staff. Personally speaking, I have seen them use a knife to help fold a sub by placing it in between the two buns. Everyone fills their sub with different fillings, from non-vegetarian to vegetarian choices. As such, this again creates cross-contamination concerns. Even more alarming, every time before folding each sub, they clean the knife with a musty hand towel — when’s the last time they cleaned that towel?</p> <p>I agree with most of the points they made during the deliberation and feel their approaches, especially on diversifying food options here, would go a long way to bettering dining life here. Hopefully, dining authorities listen to their policies or programs so that something can be implemented sometime in the future. Getting food shouldn’t need to be a hassle, so it’s best the university acts quickly to make things easier for people like me.</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="food-wastage"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sinkholes: Can we forecast a catastrophic collapse?</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/sinkholes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sinkholes: Can we forecast a catastrophic collapse?"/><published>2023-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/sinkholes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/sinkholes/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>It’s a frightening thought to imagine the ground below your feet or house suddenly collapsing and forming a big hole in the ground, but that’s the unfortunate reality. Fortunately, sinkholes rarely happen, but when they strike, tragedy can occur — in fact, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/mar/01/man-disappears-sinkhole-florida">a Florida man</a> was mysteriously swallowed by a sinkhole underneath his bedroom not too long ago! As you can already guess, a sinkhole is simply a hole in the ground, ranging anywhere from shallow holes about one meter deep to pits more than fifty meters deep. But it forms when water dissolves surface rock, typically being of limestone which is easily eroded by the movement of water. They occur naturally, particularly where there is abundant rainfall like the Amazon Rainforest. Based on recent sightings and news stories, the most damage from sinkholes often occurs in Alabama, Florida, Kentucky, Missouri, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, and Texas here in the US.</p> <p>In a landscape where limestone sits directly underneath the soil, water from rainfall collects in cracks in the stone. Gradually, as the limestone dissolves by erosion and is carried away, the cracks naturally widen until the ground above them becomes unstable and collapses. The collapse often happens very suddenly and without very much warning. Water collects in these collapsed sections, forming sinkholes. Sinkholes also form when the roofs of caves collapse and cave in. Sinkholes are often funnel-shaped, with the larger end open to the light and surface and the narrow end at the bottom of a pool. Water can drain through a sinkhole into an underground channel or a cave. When mud or fine residue plugs one of these underground caves, it fills with water to become a lake or a pond.</p> <p>A cenote is a type of sinkhole that forms when the roof of an underground cave collapses, revealing the water to the surface. Cenotes are very common on the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico. There are nearly two thousand cenotes on the Yucatan, and they are a primary source of freshwater for residents there. Interestingly, Ancient Mayans once believed cenotes were passageways to the underworld.</p> <p>Sinkholes can definitely be human-induced at times, too. We can create sinkholes when building roads, aquifers, or other types of construction. Altering the land’s stability in these ways can weaken the underlying rock and make it more susceptible to sinkholes. Sinkholes can open up in the middle of busy streets or in neighborhoods, especially during heavy rainfall.</p> <p>As a fun fact, the land surrounding the Dead Sea in the Middle East is prone to sinkholes because of the prevalence of rock salt, which is readily dissolved by water. Tourists who are unaware of sinkholes and even scientists studying sinkholes have been injured by falling into them.</p> <hr/> <p>Pearson, M. (2013, March 4). <i>Sinkholes: Common, costly and sometimes deadly</i>. CNN. Retrieved April 2, 2023, from https://www.cnn.com/2013/03/01/us/florida-sinkhole-explainer/index.html</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/sinkholes-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/sinkholes-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/sinkholes-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/sinkholes.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural-phenomena"/><category term="sinkholes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Science Behind a Shooting Star!</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/shooting-stars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Science Behind a Shooting Star!"/><published>2023-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/shooting-stars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/shooting-stars/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Falling stars, more commonly known as shooting stars, are meteors or other pieces of matter that burn up and disintegrate as they enter the Earth’s atmosphere and pass through it. Surprisingly, over 25 million meteors hit the Earth’s atmosphere every day.</p> <p>It is important to understand the difference between the terms meteor and meteorite. The difference between the two is that a meteorite is a piece of matter, typically made of rock, that passes through the Earth’s atmosphere and hits its surface. Meteors are pieces of matter that burn up in the Earth’s atmosphere but never hit the ground. Essentially, meteorites are meteors that survive their fall through the Earth’s atmosphere.</p> <p>What causes shooting stars? Everyone knows that there are many pieces of matter, such as rock or dust, floating through space. Some pieces of matter happen to pass near Earth and get caught by Earth’s gravitational field. However, some pieces of rock were already on a direct course to hit Earth. Once these small pieces of matter enter the Earth’s atmosphere, the meteor falls at an incredibly high speed, ranging from 25,000 mph to 160,000 mph on average. The speed of the fall against the gasses of the atmosphere creates intense friction. The friction causes the surface of the small piece of matter to burn up, which is called ablation. In fact, rapid heat generation is responsible for the light that we see from gazing across the night sky. Very small meteors burn up or vaporize before they can even hit the Earth’s surface. The larger meteors that survive the atmospheric friction hit the Earth’s surface and become meteorites. The meteors that survive are much smaller when they hit the ground because they burned during their fall.</p> <p>But why do we call them shooting stars? Shooting star seems logical as a descriptor because stargazers see the streak of light produced as a meteor falls through the atmosphere. The streak of light allows us to see the meteor fall — or “shoot” — across the sky. We associate glowing in the sky with stars, so a burning meteor seems like a star moving across the sky.</p> <p>Shooting stars are occurring all the time, even during the day. The best time to see one is at night since one can readily see the trail it leaves behind. It is also best to find a location away from cities and light pollution. The sky will be darkest in the countryside, away from man-produced lights. The darker the sky, the better chance one has of seeing one. Also, there’s an increased chance of seeing one during a meteor shower. A meteor shower consists of several pieces of a comet that have been left behind or broke off the comet. When the Earth passes through this field of debris, the pieces burn up in the atmosphere.</p> <hr/> <p>Dobrijevic, D. (2022, August 11). <i>Meteor showers and shooting stars: Formation and history</i>. Space.com. Retrieved March 28, 2023, from https://www.space.com/meteor-showers-shooting-stars.html</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/shooting-stars-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/shooting-stars-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/shooting-stars-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/shooting-stars.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural-phenomena"/><category term="shooting-stars"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Issue Brief Introduction</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/issue-brief-intro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Issue Brief Introduction"/><published>2023-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/issue-brief-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/issue-brief-intro/"><![CDATA[<div> <b>Regulating Medical Devices with AI Capabilities: Healthcare assistant or tyrant?</b> <hr/> <p>The rapid rise of innovative technology is augmenting human capabilities and replacing eons-old activities. Artificial intelligence (AI)-driven systems have particularly spread to more than half of the world’s population in ambient information and connectivity, with new advances constantly being made like DeepMind’s AlphaFold AI-based algorithm that solved a 50-year-old challenge in proteomics. As AI technology continues to evolve at an alarming rate, it’s being integrated with and deployed into a variety of sectors, such as the automotive, finance, manufacturing, retail, and, most notably, the healthcare industry where it has surged in popularity over the past few years. Indeed, medical AI promises to drive tremendous scientific breakthroughs, aid in diagnosis, treatment, and management of diseases, accelerate drug development and delivery, control costs, and support health equity. While some strongly praise this emerging power, others believe its a double-edged sword with potential risks that may bring considerable threats, including potential errors and patient harm; risks of bias and increased health inequalities; lack of transparency and trust; and vulnerability to hacking and data privacy breaches to name a few. Although these reservations likely won’t obstruct its adoption into healthcare in the long run, these are valid points that must be addressed appropriately to ward off exacerbated concerns. The regulatory framework governing these tools is complex. For example, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulates some AI-enabled products used in healthcare, and the agency plays an important role in ensuring the safety and effectiveness of those products under its jurisdiction. Right now, the agency is considering how to adapt its review process for AI-enabled medical devices that have the ability to evolve rapidly in response to new data, sometimes in ways that are difficult to anticipate. Ultimately, it will require a joint effort by key authorities like the FDA, Congress, technology developers, and the healthcare industry to ensure the safety and effectiveness of medical AI-enabled technology, maximizing the benefits while minimizing these risks at the same time.</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="issue-brief-intro"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brinicles: The Icy Fingers of Death</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/brinicles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brinicles: The Icy Fingers of Death"/><published>2023-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/brinicles</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/brinicles/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>On the 2011 British nature documentary series <i>Frozen Planet</i>, Alec Baldwin once described brinicles as “icy fingers of death” because of their deadly nature. Concretely speaking, brinicles are underwater stalactites, or hollow icicles, that form when cold saltwater freezes.</p> <p>These underwater icicles are made possible by brine channels that form in the ice on the ocean’s surface. When sea ice forms in the Arctic and Antarctic, impurities like salt are forced out, which is why ice created from seawater isn’t as salty as the water from which it’s formed. As this salty water leaks from the sea ice, the surrounding water becomes more saline, increasing its density and lowering its freezing point temperature. This prevents the water from freezing to the ice and causes it to sink to the bottom. As this cold brine reaches warmer seawater below, the water freezes around it through heat transfer, creating a tubular-shaped ice known as a brinicle. When this sea stalactite reaches the seabed, a web of ice forms and spreads to its surroundings, freezing everything it touches — including any sea life it encounters, such as starfish and sea urchins — which is how brinicles earned themselves a reputation as “icy fingers of death.” Pools of super-cold brine may also form and remain beneath the site of brinicle formation. These so-called “black pools of death” can also be deadly to slow-moving, bottom-dwelling sea creatures that pass through them accidentally.</p> <p>Fortunately, brinicles are not dangerous to humans, as we rarely travel beneath the ice sheets where they form. However, divers who study brinicles take precautions to avoid hypothermia or other cold water injuries.</p> <p>Brine can be beneficial within the sea ice: it may warm and melt through the ice, moving heat from one part of the ice to the other. They also provide an ideal habitat for microscopic plants and animals, particularly diatoms (a type of algae) which sometimes stain the ice a dark brownish green.</p> <p>If you thought underwater icicles were a surreal phenomenon, underwater lakes are even better. When the temperature of brine is not freezing, brine seeping into the ocean can form brine pools, with shorelines and all. Shockingly, brine lakes can range from 3 feet to 12 miles long in the Gulf of Mexico! These lakes are created by a process called salt tectonics, which refers to the movement of large salt deposits.</p> <p>In 2011, the crew of <i>Frozen Planet</i> became the first to film a brinicle formation. They used time lapse photography to capture the event over the course of several hours. Their first attempt was unsuccessful, since large seals in the area knocked over their camera equipment and broke delicate, fledgling brinicle structures. See a short clip of their footage below.</p> <hr/> <p>Ripley’s Believe It or Not!, et al. “The Science of Brinicle: Ice Stalactites.” <i>Ripley’s Believe It or Not!</i>, 28 Apr. 2017, https://www.ripleys.com/weird-news/brinciles-ice-stalactite/.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/brinicles-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/brinicles-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/brinicles-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/brinicles.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lAupJzH31tc" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural-phenomena"/><category term="brinicles"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Climate Change Crisis: A Reflection of its Reality</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/climate-change-crisis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Climate Change Crisis: A Reflection of its Reality"/><published>2023-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/climate-change-crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/climate-change-crisis/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Over the past decade, the ongoing climate change crisis has been a highly-debated concern for many people. Individuals’ stances on this issue often differ based on what political party they align themselves with, as climate change and global warming were, and still are, very politically charged topics. In fact, in <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-fix/wp/2013/04/22/how-americans-see-global-warming-in-8-charts/">2013</a>, 85% of Democrats said that they believed that there was solid evidence supporting global warming, while only 48% of Republicans responded in this way. In <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2023/08/09/what-the-data-says-about-americans-views-of-climate-change/">2022</a>, however, roughly two-thirds of Democrats (65%) say addressing climate change should be a top priority for Biden and Congress, compared with just 11% of Republicans. Evidently, there’s a declining trend for support over the past few years, but why’s it the case? Although both parties differ on various topics prevalent in our community today, they agree that other “high-demanding” concerns like abortion rights, healthcare policy, immigration policy, and taxes to name a few outweigh the crisis. Some people believe that such issues are problems of the present and should be resolved as quickly as possible, while putting other long-term issues like the climate change crisis “on the back burner” to be dealt with at a later time. However, it’s crucial that we take steps beforehand towards alleviating its effects because who knows what life on earth will be like in the future if we don’t take rapid action to cut emissions.</p> <p><a href="https://www.edf.org/climate/9-ways-we-know-humans-triggered-climate-change">97%</a> of scientists say humans are the cause of global warming, mainly attributed to the increased burning of fossil fuels. Ever since the Industrial Revolution, there has been 40% more carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. And right now, we are adding 70 million metric tons of carbon dioxide to the atmosphere on a daily basis. Given these harsh realities, President Biden outlined a bold plan a few years back — a Clean Energy Revolution — to address this threat and lead the world in addressing the climate emergency. There are nine key points to his plan: (1) take executive action to not just reverse all of the damage Trump has done, but go further and faster, (2) work with Congress to enact legislation that puts us on an irreversible path to achieve economy-wide net-zero emissions no later than 2050, (3) rally the world to urgent and additional action, (4) make investments in clean energy and innovation, (5) accelerate the deployment of clean technology throughout our economy, (6) make environmental justice a priority across all federal agencies, (7) hold polluters accountable, (8) create 10 million good-paying, middle-class, union jobs, and finally (9) fulfill our obligation to the communities and workers that have risked their lives to produce fossil fuels that made it possible for America to win world wars and become an industrial superpower. While creating such a plan is encouraging, not everyone will, of course, share similar views and be supportive of this initiative. And so, will President Biden’s declaration affirming the reality of the crisis be enough to convince the general populace to take action?</p> <p>According to a recent Pew Research study done on Earth Day 2022, a 54% majority of adults under 30 believe the crisis should be a top priority, compared with smaller shares of Americans ages 30 to 49 (42%), ages 50 to 64 (36%) and ages 65 and older (39%). But why do older populations fail to realize the severity of the crisis? Some say that other health concerns consume their minds, while others argue that they are “on their deathbed” and, consequently, can’t do much.</p> <p>In order to make any significant progress in reducing emissions to curb climate change, it is imperative that the general public become more informed about the topic, and recognize it as a serious threat to the human way of life — perhaps not right away, but definitely a threat to the quality of life experienced by our children and our children’s children. Moreover, people need to forget the polarizing politics associated with the issue. Once these things are accomplished, it will be possible for individuals to take action and collectively bring about a positive change. Additionally, once political stigma surrounding the issue is reduced and dissolved, policymakers will be able to move forward and carry out the necessary steps to pass legislation for a positive impact.</p> <p>Take Antarctica as an example. Antarctica is rich in precious natural resources like ice, coal, metallic minerals, petroleum. A rise in global temperature has led to the warming of the Antarctic Peninsula, breaking the continent’s ice sheet and, consequently, decreasing the continent’s local species populations. Realistically speaking, human-caused issues put at risk the last pristine continent in the world, containing the world’s biggest source of freshwater, huge potential oil and natural gas reserves, and the key to determining how climate change will affect the world through rising sea levels.</p> <p>Many organizations worldwide have already taken measures to combat the issue and alleviate the effects. For example, in the automotive industry, Tesla has already produced nearly 1.91 million electric vehicles since 2009, in accordance with its mission to “accelerate the world’s transition into sustainable energy.” Additionally, at least 92.7 billion solar panels have been installed across the world today, producing cleaner energy (i.e., electricity) that keeps us from burning fossil fuels. Some proposals for the future involve cooling Earth’s surface by spraying artificially-made, reflective particles into the planet’s atmosphere, scattering and reflecting sunlight back into space. Other proposals involve sowing the oceans with iron to cause large-scale phytoplankton growth, thereby removing carbon dioxide from the atmosphere through photosynthesis. Such methods could potentially work but require further research.</p> <p>The climate change crisis is certainly a widely-overlooked issue in today’s world, though a minority does realize its importance and severity if left alone. Therefore, it’s of great importance that everyone is informed of its effects, especially our children who will carry on this mission into the future. All in all, everyone, regardless of political affiliation, has a responsibility to limit climate change, no matter how big or small of an impact it makes.</p> <hr/> <p>“Climate Change.” <i>ITU</i>, https://www.itu.int/en/mediacentre/backgrounders/Pages/climate-change.aspx.</p> <p>Clement, Scott. “How Americans See Global Warming – in 8 Charts.” <i>The Washington Post</i>, WP Company, 26 Nov. 2021, https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-fix/wp/2013/04/22/how-americans-see-global-warming-in-8-charts/.</p> <p>Schaeffer, Katherine. “For Earth Day, Key Facts about Americans’ Views of Climate Change and Renewable Energy.” <i>Pew Research Center</i>, Pew Research Center, 22 Apr. 2022, https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/04/22/for-earth-day-key-facts-about-americans-views-of-climate-change-and-renewable-energy/.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/climate-change-crisis-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/climate-change-crisis-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/climate-change-crisis-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/climate-change-crisis.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="climate-change"/><category term="climate-change-crisis"/><category term="global-warming"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Glowing Beaches: Understanding the Natural Wonder of Bioluminescence</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/glowing-beaches/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glowing Beaches: Understanding the Natural Wonder of Bioluminescence"/><published>2023-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/glowing-beaches</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/glowing-beaches/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Have you ever heard about the natural ocean wonder of bioluminescence? It’s when the sea glows either a neon blue or green, or even red in some rare cases. The ocean can sparkle and glitter like the stars in the sky because of a chemical reaction known as bioluminescence, which allows some living things to emit light from their body. Bioluminescence is considered <i>cold light</i>, meaning that less than 20% of the light generates thermal radiation or any other form of heat. This fact is mainly responsible for the bluish and whitish color. Sea creatures like some algae, crustaceans, fish, and squid species perform bioluminescence in order to fool their predators, attract their prey, or even lure possible mates. However, as a side note, many of us have seen various bioluminescent organisms on land such as fireflies and fungi.</p> <p>As you might already predict, this phenomenon usually occurs in the night time when there is little light, as it’s easier to see the colors. Typically, we can witness this phenomenon when there is lots of bioluminescence in the water, most commonly from an algae bloom of plankton. The water will glow when it’s disturbed by a wave breaking or a splash in the water at night. Algae bloom sea sparkle events are caused by a combination of calm and warm sea conditions. But you can see specks of bioluminescence when it’s created nearby by a light-producing marine creature.</p> <p>In some cases, it is safe to swim in bioluminescent waters. However, in other cases, swimming in bioluminescent water may prove to be dangerous, for some bioluminescent species release toxins into water that can potentially poison fish, humans, and other creatures that come into contact with it. So all in all, it’s mainly best to avoid swimming in bioluminescent waters, just to be safe. In fact, at the most famous bioluminescence location in the world, the Mosquito Bay in Puerto Rico, swimming with the organisms is no longer permitted.</p> <p>Believe it or not, human skin is considered to be bioluminescent. According to a recent study done by Japanese researchers, human bioluminescence is possible and exists in visible light, but, sadly, our eyes are inherently unable to see this wavelength of light — for nerds, roughly a thousand times lower than what we can see with just our naked eyes. Using hyper-sensitive cameras, the team monitored volunteers for twenty minutes every three hours in a dark, tightly-shut room for days. The experts came to the conclusion that the human body actually glows like other bioluminescent organisms, with the brightest parts being the cheeks, forehead, and neck. This process in our bodies does not work in the same way for other bioluminescent organisms, for it is really more of our own form of glowing bioluminescence.</p> <p>Sparkling night lights have been photographed across Australia, Maldives, Puerto Rico, the Everglades, and many more sea-bordering sites across the world, attracting tourists from around the world to be awe-stricken — in fact, the above image was taken from Henley Beach in South Australia.</p> <hr/> <p><i>You Are Being Redirected…</i>, https://travelzone.bestwestern.com/4-unbelievable-bioluminescent-beaches-usa/.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/glowing-beaches-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/glowing-beaches-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/glowing-beaches-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/glowing-beaches.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural-phenomena"/><category term="glowing-beaches"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>