<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://asen4.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://asen4.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-24T02:27:40+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Post COVID-19 Pandemic: A Reflection of the Current State of the World</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/covid19-reflection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post COVID-19 Pandemic: A Reflection of the Current State of the World"/><published>2022-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/covid19-reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/covid19-reflection/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Ever since the pandemic broke out in December 2019, it has increased individualism among us. The pandemic has changed the nature of our “typical” social interactions; we don’t interact with other people in-person as much anymore. Many of us would agree that video calling can be a nicer way of chatting with others because it lets us physically see and speak to anyone regardless of where they are in the world, which was especially true with the rise in loneliness during the pandemic. As Zoom dominated — and continues to dominate — the video-calling industry, we shift to it as our main form of communication with others: in-person meetings are closer to becoming obsolete essentially, as video-calling becomes the new trend in today’s developing world. And even work life, too! Take the technology industry as an example. Company leaders have witnessed a significant boost in work output as they allow their employees to work from home on a few days in the weeks, and, consequently, some have implemented hybrid-working policies.</p> <p>There have been studies that show more than 90% of data generated in the world have been in the last few years. Almost every year, there are new advances in artificial intelligence (AI) like OpenAI’s language model that uses deep learning to produce human-like text, alarmingly indistinguishable deep-fake videos and images, or DeepMind’s AlphaFold AIbased algorithm that solved a 50-year old challenge in proteomics. Therefore, I have no doubt that this field will continue to grow in the coming decades. However, at the same time, the evolution of technology goes to make sure that tasks that humans could do earlier can now be achieved by machines and technology, therefore creating a shortage of jobs. And even more concerning, a rise in technology has created a dependence on our devices, tools, and processes. There’s not a requirement to think or recall information because everything is instantly available to us in a giant database, the Internet. Even a little tool, like a calculator, reduces the necessity to perform mental calculations or skills to try to do mathematics because you’ll solve equations by crunching them into the device that “magically” spits out answers/numbers. With regards to the recent COVID-19 pandemic, it caused an inevitable surge in the use of digital technologies due to the social distancing norms and nationwide lockdowns instituted in place; as such, video-conferencing platforms like Zoom were on the rise to build and maintain relationships. This embodies the commonplace of reliance on technology, as people become more reliant and overuse technology to the point where it’s unnecessary — some people are video calling their neighbors who live two minutes away from them!</p> <p>Homeschooling was also on the rise with the outbreak of the pandemic. As schools were not able to provide ideal in-person instruction anymore, young children were less likely to attend Zoom lecture videos and, consequently, were not able to easily grasp concepts and fundamental ideas. Furthermore, older students like high school students and college students took advantage of the situation and, quite frankly, cheated on examinations. Essentially, the pandemic has taught us that online instruction is an unfavorable form of instruction that shouldn’t be repeated again in the future, unless absolutely necessary because of the circumstances. This embodies the commonplace of in-person instruction reigning as the most efficient form of teaching, not online instruction.</p> <p>With the pandemic’s brutal waves, the US and other countries will hopefully realize in the following years that working together will help solve problems that are on a global scale. Through seeing the spread of the COVID-19 variants in the US, countries will realize that this is a global problem, not a US problem. In the coming years, we will also hopefully see more economic safety nets put in place like the COVID stimulus package that the citizens will be less stressed, more supportive, and inclusive of their communities — that’s the long-term goal!</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/covid19-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/covid19-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/covid19-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/covid19-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/covid19-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/covid19-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/covid19-2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/covid19-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="covid19"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ideas for History of a Public Controversy Project</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/history-of-a-controversy-project-ideas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ideas for History of a Public Controversy Project"/><published>2022-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/history-of-a-controversy-project-ideas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/history-of-a-controversy-project-ideas/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Gun violence has been a highly-debated topic in the country for the last several years. At a time, it seemed like there was either a mass shooting or other act of gun violence everyday, although the situation has normalized in the past few months. While some gun control advocates uphold and support the Second Amendment, others feel they are a harm towards our safety at large.</p> <p>Maybe we could also consider doing something on universal healthcare. While universal healthcare already exists in countries like Sweden, Hong Kong, and Kuwait, where the local and federal government pays for most costs associated with healthcare coverage, there has been widespread disagreement over how to control high insurance costs, bureaucratic treatment obstacles, and deep socioeconomic inequalities.</p> <p>The Russian-Ukrainian conflict could also be considered another option. Was it ethical? We would, of course, have to examine the relationships between Russia and Ukraine over history, delving more into the issue from the perspective of both sides.</p> <p>We could also consider the climate change crisis. Is global warming real? Is it caused mainly by human activity? How harmful is it likely to be? What can we do about it? Some skeptics argue that the dangers of climate change are exaggerated, while others accept global warming as real but dismiss evidence that suggests it’s connected to human activity. Government regulation, suppression of scientific data for political gain, and international agreements on climate change often play a role in the debate.</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="history-of-a-public-controversy-project"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is a maze, literally and metaphorically speaking!</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/mazes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is a maze, literally and metaphorically speaking!"/><published>2022-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/mazes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/mazes/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Life is filled with mazes. My two biggest interests have been working through mind-bending logic puzzles and building my own convoluted contraptions. Solving a puzzle or creating a machine is much like navigating through the twists and turns of a maze—sometimes you think of a solution that works, and at other times you run into “dead ends.” What will you do then? Well, these “dead ends” are exciting to me because they are opportunities to try an even more clever approach. Whether it be sitting stumped for hours on a logic puzzle or troubleshooting the root cause of a malfunction in a gadget, each challenge is like a game in my eyes, motivating me to keep pushing forward and think of alternative avenues until I reach the correct answer or have a working product. <b>As a matter of fact, my joy for challenges stems back to my first puzzles: nonograms, Sudokus, metal wire puzzles, and board games.</b></p> <p>To most, it might seem like there’s not enough information to solve these puzzles at first, but that’s part of the fun—taking them one step at a time while searching for subtle clues. After many of these steps, the progress compounds and it becomes even more motivating to make more steps. From decrypting a grid to reveal the hidden mosaic in a nonogram to deducing which numbers should be placed where in a Sudoku, I revel in solving all kinds of logic puzzles. And even physical ones, too: in my free time, I’ll usually try to disentangle the interlocked metal wire pieces. Applying the same logical and levelheaded approach, I also find that strategy games like chess, <i>Risk</i>, and <i>Settlers of Catan</i> give me an opportunity to exercise logic in a creative way. In fact, I sometimes spend hours after a game thinking of “what-if” strategies on how I could have done better.</p> <p>Working on these puzzles have even helped teach me to think systematically at day-to-day obstacles I see in my own life. Take as an example the time my family found small water spots within our attic. To better understand if these spots were signs of water leakage from old or damaged roof shingles, we needed to have a bird’s-eye view of our roof. Using a small old remote-controlled helicopter toy, an Arduino (a microcontroller platform that controls specialized pieces of hardware using code), a tiny camera module, a power module, and a storage module, I built a makeshift drone for practically free. Coming up with the idea was the easy part; executing it, though, proved to be the real challenge. I started by building a functional video component on the original Arduino board. Then, incrementally, I tried to enable video recording with the camera and storage module. Lastly, I tried attaching all the modules to the toy helicopter in a way that would still enable the helicopter to achieve liftoff with the additional weight. By breaking down this task into smaller and more manageable pieces, I learned it makes the entire building process significantly easier. Ultimately, this new gadget let me see my roof, record the entire flight, and examine the recorded footage at various magnification settings. We found there to be no distinctly misplaced or damaged shingle, but it did give me the chance to play with some new Arduino components that I had not known before.</p> <p><b>My “dead ends” make me continually look at things differently, but I know others have their own types of challenges. My “dead ends” challenge me to an extent in which I can find enjoyment in them. My “dead ends” shape my entire life, as odd as it sounds to say that!</b> But, the thing with “dead ends” in mazes is that they teach you to be open to other pathways. As I said before, my life is full of mazes with “dead ends!”</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/mazes-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/mazes-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/mazes-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/mazes.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fun-posts"/><category term="arduino"/><category term="logic-puzzles"/><category term="metal-wire-puzzles"/><category term="puzzles"/><category term="mazes"/><category term="sudoku"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bringing Back Memories: My First App TagOut!</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/tagout/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bringing Back Memories: My First App TagOut!"/><published>2022-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/tagout</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/tagout/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>After playing video games for years, I started wondering how I could make better or more customizable games. So, I began exploring how I could create games on my own using code. I started building classic games like <i>Angry Birds</i>, <i>Flappy Bird</i>, <i>Snake</i>, and <i>Tetris</i>. Wanting to explore other use cases for coding, I pursued Android application development in my high school years. Starting out, I felt completely overwhelmed! I downloaded Android Studio, the official integrated development environment for Google’s Android operating system, and was taken aback by all the thousands of buttons and functionalities. I quickly realized I wasn’t ready to jump headfirst into this new experience.</p> <p>And so, with the guidance and inspiration from my brother, I read various informative articles, viewed YouTube tutorial videos, and finally enrolled in a few online Udacity courses on Android application development. For the first few months, I had the task of creating my own apps (as assignments for the courses) and expanding on the starter code to develop additional features. For example, I first developed an app called <i>Miwok</i>, intending to provide beginners and newbies pronunciation and writing lessons to Miwok. (Miwok is a language spoken by members of an indigenous Native American tribe.) After spending days after days taking several courses, I finally decided to get to work and build a social media by myself, without any handholding. Starting out, I slowly tried to build individual pieces of the app, instead of focusing on the entire problem as a whole. As many say, “to make it easier on yourself, break down the problem into smaller, easier to solve problems.” I worked first on developing a login and registration page and implementing the Google Sign-In feature. As I moved onto the posting feature, I tried to focus on designing a friendly user interface and storing post information in my realtime database. As I moved onto the messaging feature, I realized I need to import a vast number of open-source software packages that I never knew about before and store messages and image files in Firebase Storage, a place to upload and store user generated content. Without diving too much into the technical details, the entire process took nearly six months. It was definitely a worthwhile experience, as it provided confidence and pushed me to develop my future apps.</p> <p>Today, this app is available on the Google Play Store and called <i>TagOut!</i>. (<b>Isn’t this a great name?</b>) <i>TagOut!</i> is a platform designed to maximize social interaction between users. It also enables users to message with one another and send pictures/documents instantly too!</p> <p>If you were interested, see <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.anubhav.helloapplication">this link</a> for more information about <i>TagOut!</i>.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/tagout-feature-graphic-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/tagout-feature-graphic-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/tagout-feature-graphic-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tagout-feature-graphic.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <i>TagOut! Feature Graphic</i> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fun-posts"/><category term="android"/><category term="app"/><category term="social-media"/><category term="tagout!"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TED Talk Slideshow</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/ted-talk-slideshow/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TED Talk Slideshow"/><published>2022-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/ted-talk-slideshow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/ted-talk-slideshow/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Please see <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1wd11iYb9PpMUHiEmVmmgJHEeGECyu3lofQqfvZbeKak/edit?usp=sharing">this link</a> for a copy of my TED Talk slideshow.</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="other"/><category term="ted-talk"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Smart Planner: A New Digital Student Planner Application</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/smart-planner/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Smart Planner: A New Digital Student Planner Application"/><published>2022-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/smart-planner</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/smart-planner/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>As my teacher finished his lecture, I took a quick glance at the homework board to see the due dates for upcoming assignments. Seeing so much work to do this weekend, I took between, say, thirty seconds to a minute scribbling down the due dates into my handy-dandy planner. As I headed over to the next class, I saw the homework board and realized I have more work to do. Groaning, I took roughly thirty seconds copying down the due dates into my planner. At the next class, I spent between a minute to two minutes writing down the due dates. The cycle repeats again and again, where, by the end of the day, I wasted nearly three to six minutes writing down the due dates. To make matters worse, I forgot to do my chemistry homework because I forcibly crammed the due date into the bottom corner of my planner. “You silly, how careless of you! It’s so tiny that it’s barely even legible. It’s no wonder you <b>foolishly forgot</b> to do it,” my teacher bursts laughing in response to my dilemma.</p> <p><i>Can’t this time be better used somewhere else?</i> I thought. Maybe I could be chatting with my friends or ask the teacher a question on something I didn’t understand quite well. Essentially wouldn’t it be better if these reminders were automatically written in a safe place everyday?</p> <p>Many people questioningly said, “<b>You’re going to try to accomplish something similar to the degree of Noah’s ark?</b> You!?” Nevertheless, I trudged onwards. Spending most of the past summer developing this app (<i>Smart Planner</i>), I encountered many obstacles and, consequently, spent hours after hours debugging my code. Although it may sound like a chore to many, I found it enjoyable as I navigated through the twists and turns to find the root cause of the issue — this is yet another example of how programming, specifically debugging, can be treated similar to solving a puzzle. Sometimes I collaborated with others who faced similar issues on Stack Overflow (a question and answer website for programmers); they challenged my preconceptions and presented approaches that I never thought of before. At other times, the solution came as an “aha” moment after scanning through hundreds of lines of code and brainstorming creative reasons behind errors. Essentially, programming is almost like being a detective — go to multiple sources, collect various bits of information, and finally put the pieces together.</p> <p>Unless you’re like a few select people who can memorize the due dates and keep track of everything in your head, then get <i>Smart Planner</i>! Instead of having to write assignment deadlines on the homework board everyday, professors have the ability to create assignment reminders in the app in just 1-2 minutes. Students can look at these reminders whenever they wish throughout the day. Any user can also give comments and ratings to other users, regardless of whether they’re professors or students (similar to <a href="https://www.ratemyprofessors.com/">Rate My Professors</a>). Say goodbye to outdated paper daily planners (and deforestation), and say hello to <i>Smart Planner</i>! Happy planning — and studying!</p> <p>If you were interested, see <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.anubhav.assignmentsfeed">this link</a> for more information about <i>Smart Planner</i>.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/smart-planner-feature-graphic-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/smart-planner-feature-graphic-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/smart-planner-feature-graphic-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/smart-planner-feature-graphic.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <i>Smart Planner Feature Graphic</i> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fun-posts"/><category term="android"/><category term="app"/><category term="organizational-needs"/><category term="planner"/><category term="smart-planner"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Favorite TED Talk &amp;amp; Unit Two Project Ideas</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/favorite-ted-talk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Favorite TED Talk &amp;amp; Unit Two Project Ideas"/><published>2022-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/favorite-ted-talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/favorite-ted-talk/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>In 2014, the world avoided an outbreak of Ebola, thanks to the care and generosity provided by thousands of health workers — not to mention sheer dumb luck, too. The following year, Bill Gates was invited to a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZLkbWUNQbgk">TED Talk</a> and emphasized our lack of preparation as the root cause of the damage. He urged us to accelerate practices like scenario planning, vaccine research, and health worker training in preparation for the next pandemic. And seven years later, we see that the COVID-19 pandemic has dawned onto the world and broken out in several deadly waves since 2019; the Trump administration’s failure to respond appropriately and promptly to the pandemic exacerbated the situation, leading to the subsequent economic crisis. I enjoyed watching this TED Talk because it’s somewhat funny to see nobody paying heed to Gates’s warnings. He did all the work and created a plan and outlined all the steps to avoid another outbreak, but nobody listened to him — and our failure to listen has landed the world in today’s current situation, where everybody still fears contracting the coronavirus even though the situation has died down.</p> <p>As for my Unit Two project, I was considering talking about the evolution of the word ‘pandemic’ and if we have prepared or taken any action in fighting pandemics within the past few decades. In the past few years, has anybody ever given warnings to the entire world, in anticipation of another impending global outbreak (like Gates did in 2015)? I would use the Gale Virtual Reference Library to track the evolution of the word ‘pandemic’ and how it’s definition has changed within the past few years. Alternatively, I was considering looking into the evolution of the climate change crisis and researching what actions we have taken to combat the issue. Besides transitioning to electric vehicles, installing solar panels, and researching innovating techniques to cool the Earth, what other meaningful contributions have we made that are sometimes overlooked today? At what rate have we worsened the situation in the past few years? These are some simple questions to consider that could be a part of my research in determining the evolution of the climate change crisis.</p> </div> <hr/> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZLkbWUNQbgk" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="other"/><category term="ted-talk"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Freewriting is like solving a puzzle!</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/java-a-comprehensive-guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Freewriting is like solving a puzzle!"/><published>2022-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/java-a-comprehensive-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/java-a-comprehensive-guide/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>“What’s a variable?”</p> <p>“Is a class a blueprint to make objects?”</p> <p>“Do objects contain attributes and methods?”</p> <p>My mini online Java lectures were often accompanied by a series of these questions. As I answered these questions, it brought back fond memories of my days as a beginner. Seeing fascinating and novel advances in artificial intelligence like OpenAI’s language model that uses deep learning to produce human-like text and alarmingly indistinguishable deep-fake videos and images, I became hooked and enrolled in various online courses and watched online YouTube videos with the main intent of learning Java.</p> <p>Four years have passed, and I’ve reached proficiency today. Wanting to pass on my knowledge, I decided to start a small tutoring session service within my locality. I wanted to ensure that all my students (i.e., a mix of elementary and middle schoolers) walked away with a thorough understanding of the fundamentals. But as each weekly session passed with students simply memorizing concepts and little to no curiosity, this didn’t seem satisfying anymore.</p> <p><i>How could I make a broader impact on those who were eager to learn Java like I once was, in a readily accessible format?</i> I thought. This was the fundamental question.</p> <p>And so, this chain of thoughts urged me to author a two-part written guide to the basics and advanced concepts of Java. With no experience authoring a book before, I quickly realized the real challenge was compiling the information and determining how to organize the content effectively: in other words, I wanted to mimic a textbook’s style, in which it starts with the absolute basics and gradually builds up to the abstract topics. Determining how to phrase the content simply so as to make it easy for readers to understand, providing ample exercise problems, and writing succinctly were other important factors to consider as I crafted together the guide. In general, this leisure activity made me realize how writing is like solving a puzzle. Writing is, by no means, a linear process. You’re solving a puzzle. It’s important to place some of your pieces on the puzzleboard and worry about adding, deleting, and embellishing finer points later. You necessarily don’t have to start with the first piece (i.e., the introduction), you can start with the sixth or the hundredth piece (i.e., a body paragraph or a separate chapter) alternatively. For me, treating the writing process as solving a puzzle made it more enjoyable and easier to work towards my small deadlines/goals (i.e., it didn’t seem as daunting as it initially seemed to me).</p> <p>A rigorous technical treatment, it consists of a detailed, foundational Java module and several practice problems on various topics (e.g., primary data structures, conditional statements, loops, arrays, graphics, interfaces, trees, sets, maps, and much more). It’s my hope that all those who are eager to learn have such resources handy, which I wish I possessed when I was learning programming.</p> <p>After seeing my work publicly available on Amazon, my friends jokingly commented, “<b>750 pages! Did you write one of those textbooks? I think you went a little overboard in creating your so-called comprehensive guide</b>.”</p> <p>If you were interested, see [this link] for more information about <i>Java: A Comprehensive Guide</i>.</p> [this link]: https://sites.google.com/view/anubhav-sen/software-development-projects/talkzone?authuser=0 </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <div> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/java-a-comprehensive-guide-part-i-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/java-a-comprehensive-guide-part-i-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/java-a-comprehensive-guide-part-i-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/java-a-comprehensive-guide-part-i.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0B9ZB8Z17/ref=dbs_a_def_rwt_bibl_vppi_i1">Java: A Comprehensive Guide (Part I)</a> </div> </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <div> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/java-a-comprehensive-guide-part-ii-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/java-a-comprehensive-guide-part-ii-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/java-a-comprehensive-guide-part-ii-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/java-a-comprehensive-guide-part-ii.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0B9ZLJ42B/ref=dbs_a_def_rwt_bibl_vppi_i0">Java: A Comprehensive Guide (Part II)</a> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fun-posts"/><category term="java"/><category term="java-a-comprehensive-guide"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Civic Artifacts Speeches’ Comments</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/civic-artifacts-speech-comments/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Civic Artifacts Speeches’ Comments"/><published>2022-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/civic-artifacts-speech-comments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/civic-artifacts-speech-comments/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>After viewing Emma’s speech on Penn State’s Food Waste Initiative, I really liked how she touched upon the faulty UI design of the food wastage numbers displayed here in the dining halls. She remarked on faults like one important figure being completely blocked from sight by another view and the difficulty in reading the screen as the text color blends in with the background color. I personally felt her delivery wasn’t as strong as the points she made in her presentation. She could have used more hand gestures and changed the tone of her voice to place emphasis on key points like when she was analyzing the idea of the thumbs down emoji derailing motivation and the need to preserve food.</p> <p>In my speech, I believe I could have condensed the information a bit more by spending more time talking about one attribute like Emma’s speech, not trying to name (without any further analysis) all the attributes worthy of analysis in the artifact. I could have spent more time talking about how our pursuit of advancing technology has become the byproduct of our actions from hurting Mother Nature. With regards to my delivery, I could have tried to place more emphasis on the word _our_ when mentioning how our selfishness has caused us to spread across the world and create huge changes to the atmosphere, landscapes, and ecosystems (i.e., creating advanced infrastructure through our joint efforts) without any care for their effects on the environment.</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="civic-artifacts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TalkZone: A Video-Calling/Casting Media Android Application</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/talkzone/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TalkZone: A Video-Calling/Casting Media Android Application"/><published>2022-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/talkzone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/talkzone/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Programming is like solving a logic puzzle; for me, the real joy in coding is navigating through the twists and turns at each step of the problem-solving process. As a beginner, I developed my own versions of classical games like _Angry Birds_, _Flappy Bird_, _Snake_, and _Tetris_ for the mere fun of it, frequently tackling logical problems like how to go about writing optimal algorithms and how to reduce space and time complexities if possible (i.e., the amount of time and computer memory it takes to run a piece of code). Moreover, debugging my code engaged me to brainstorm creative solutions to find the reason behind errors amidst thousands of lines of code—like a mystery game! Wanting to make a bigger impact in my work, however, I eventually turned away from video game development and pursued application development in the hopes of easing day-to-day activity for us all, starting with my family.</p> <p>My mother and my grandmother video call each other regularly, discussing their day-to-day experiences. After seeing them having difficulties communicating with each other on small, difficult to see phone screens, I decided to work with a group of friends to develop an Android application to enable them to cast their screens to larger television screens instead.</p> <p>Throughout the development process, our constant communication helped us learn more about our strengths and weaknesses and focus our expertise on the tasks most suited for our skill sets. For example, after trying to build the user interface to meet one of our self-imposed deadlines, I realized my designs were not intuitive and someone else’s was more user-friendly. So, I prioritized the underlying logic while one of my friends oversaw the application’s user interface.</p> <p>Besides the growth of my technical coding capabilities, this project ultimately taught me skills like how to get feedback from the people I work with, how to make most of my team’s individual experiences, and learning to be adaptable when things do not go according to plan. Discussion of feature implementation with my friends and family was also valuable—it made the development process engaging and helped design features we never thought of independently.</p> <p><b>We design our creations, and our creations design us (specifically our minds).</b> As we consider making a blueprint and schematic of the system, it forces us to think outside of the box, changing our neural pathways and enhancing connections between neurons.</p> <p>If you were interested, see <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.anubhav.talkzone2">this link</a> for more information about <i>TalkZone</i>.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/talkzone-feature-graphic-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/talkzone-feature-graphic-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/talkzone-feature-graphic-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/talkzone-feature-graphic.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <i>TalkZone Feature Graphic</i> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fun-posts"/><category term="android"/><category term="app"/><category term="casting"/><category term="talkzone"/><category term="video-calling"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>