<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://asen4.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://asen4.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-23T22:40:02+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2024/2023-01-17-this-i-believe-script/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2024-06-23T22:40:02+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-23T22:40:02+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2024/2023-01-17-this-i-believe-script</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2024/2023-01-17-this-i-believe-script/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Aristotle once said, “<i>The more things change, the more they stay the same</i>.” In his quest to discover the true meaning of life, he firmly believed that the universe is in a constant state of motion — always changing, always evolving. In other words, what it’s like today is never the same as tomorrow. However, he also believed in another idea that always remains constant in everything, entelechy. He preached that everything one faces must have a purpose because it gradually turns them into the person they are destined to be.</p> <p>Likewise, I believe everything happens for a reason too. Whether it’s being excluded from your friend circle or forced to run silly, time-wasting errands throughout the day, there’s often an underlying reason that most of us fail to realize. Take as an example the time my family found small water spots within our attic. To better understand if these spots were signs of water leakage from old or damaged roof shingles, we needed to have a bird’s-eye view of our roof. Using a small old remote-controlled helicopter toy, an Arduino (a microcontroller platform that controls specialized pieces of hardware using code), a tiny camera module, a power module, and a storage module, I built a makeshift drone for practically free. Coming up with the idea was the easy part, but executing it proved to be the real challenge. I started by building a functional video component on the original Arduino board. Then, incrementally, I tried to enable video recording with the camera and storage module. Lastly, I tried attaching all the modules to the toy helicopter in a way that would still enable the helicopter to achieve liftoff with the additional weight. Ultimately, this new gadget let me see my roof, record the entire flight, and examine the recorded footage at various magnification settings. We found there to be no distinctly misplaced or damaged shingle, but it did give me the chance to play with some new Arduino components.</p> <p>Had there never been any water spots to begin with, I wouldn’t have been able to step out of my comfort zone and learn more about how Arduino components work together in a system. Put another way, the leak in our roof happened so that I could explore and discover different avenues on how to come up with a solution — a test of my ability, if you will.</p> <p>As such, it’s imperative we change our outlook on how we view everyday occurrences in our daily lives, shifting towards adopting a rational mindset. If someone’s ignoring you, then you don’t have all the details yet and there’s likely to be a good reason. I believe everything happens for a reason, no matter how silly, small, or vague.</p> <p>(I know the end sounds abrupt, and I need to fix it.)</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Glowing Beaches: Understanding the Natural Wonder of Bioluminescence</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/glowing-beaches/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glowing Beaches: Understanding the Natural Wonder of Bioluminescence"/><published>2023-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/glowing-beaches</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/glowing-beaches/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Have you ever heard about the natural ocean wonder of bioluminescence? It’s when the sea glows either a neon blue or green, or even red in some rare cases. The ocean can sparkle and glitter like the stars in the sky because of a chemical reaction known as bioluminescence, which allows some living things to emit light from their body. Bioluminescence is considered <i>cold light</i>, meaning that less than 20% of the light generates thermal radiation or any other form of heat. This fact is mainly responsible for the bluish and whitish color. Sea creatures like some algae, crustaceans, fish, and squid species perform bioluminescence in order to fool their predators, attract their prey, or even lure possible mates. However, as a side note, many of us have seen various bioluminescent organisms on land such as fireflies and fungi.</p> <p>As you might already predict, this phenomenon usually occurs in the night time when there is little light, as it’s easier to see the colors. Typically, we can witness this phenomenon when there is lots of bioluminescence in the water, most commonly from an algae bloom of plankton. The water will glow when it’s disturbed by a wave breaking or a splash in the water at night. Algae bloom sea sparkle events are caused by a combination of calm and warm sea conditions. But you can see specks of bioluminescence when it’s created nearby by a light-producing marine creature.</p> <p>In some cases, it is safe to swim in bioluminescent waters. However, in other cases, swimming in bioluminescent water may prove to be dangerous, for some bioluminescent species release toxins into water that can potentially poison fish, humans, and other creatures that come into contact with it. So all in all, it’s mainly best to avoid swimming in bioluminescent waters, just to be safe. In fact, at the most famous bioluminescence location in the world, the Mosquito Bay in Puerto Rico, swimming with the organisms is no longer permitted.</p> <p>Believe it or not, human skin is considered to be bioluminescent. According to a recent study done by Japanese researchers, human bioluminescence is possible and exists in visible light, but, sadly, our eyes are inherently unable to see this wavelength of light — for nerds, roughly a thousand times lower than what we can see with just our naked eyes. Using hyper-sensitive cameras, the team monitored volunteers for twenty minutes every three hours in a dark, tightly-shut room for days. The experts came to the conclusion that the human body actually glows like other bioluminescent organisms, with the brightest parts being the cheeks, forehead, and neck. This process in our bodies does not work in the same way for other bioluminescent organisms, for it is really more of our own form of glowing bioluminescence.</p> <p>Sparkling night lights have been photographed across Australia, Maldives, Puerto Rico, the Everglades, and many more sea-bordering sites across the world, attracting tourists from around the world to be awe-stricken — in fact, the above image was taken from Henley Beach in South Australia.</p> <hr/> <p><i>You Are Being Redirected…</i>, https://travelzone.bestwestern.com/4-unbelievable-bioluminescent-beaches-usa/.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/glowing-beaches-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/glowing-beaches-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/glowing-beaches-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/glowing-beaches.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural-phenomena"/><category term="glowing-beaches"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is global starvation on the horizon?</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/global-starvation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is global starvation on the horizon?"/><published>2023-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/global-starvation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/global-starvation/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>According to the World Health Organization, the number of people globally affected by starvation rose to as many as 828 million people in 2021, an increase of approximately 46 million since 2020 and 150 million since the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic. Despite the Green Revolution taking place in the 1960s and advances in novel genetic engineering techniques to expand our food supply, the numbers still paint a grim picture of our current situation. While most people shrug off worrying about the world’s current progress in food production, why is the world hungrier than ever?</p> <p>One of the biggest and most obvious reasons is the staggering human population — in fact, the annual increase rate is estimated at 67 million people. Needless to say, there’s a long history associated with the effect of rises in the human population on food supply, starting with a bold, groundbreaking claim made by English economist Thomas Robert Malthus. In 1798, Malthus wrote an essay (<i>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as It Affects the Future Improvement of Society</i>) predicting that mass starvation would result if humans did not check their fast-growing numbers. He believed that pressures placed on our resources could lead to potentially famine and war. A debate over Malthus’ gloomy outlook sparked during his lifetime and is still occurring today. While most Anti-Malthusians believe that resources aren’t becoming scarcer, there’s still a small minority of Neo-Malthusians who believe that our resource supply won’t be able to cope with the ever-increasing human population. China and India, the world’s two most populous countries, have both relaxed their <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/06/21/1008656293/the-legacy-of-the-lasting-effects-of-chinas-1-child-policy">one-child policy</a> for quite some time now, but these troubling policies created many side effects at the time. In fact, Neo‐​Malthusian policies aimed at limiting family size increased female infanticide and sex‐​selective abortion, skewing the world’s sex ratio at birth to 107 boys per 100 girls.</p> <p>Another cause of the rapid decline in resources is global conflicts, with nearly 60% of the world’s hungry people living in areas affected by war and violence. Recent <a href="https://reliefweb.int/report/world/global-hunger-ukraine-effect-conflict-and-hunger-june-2022">events</a> such as the Russian-Ukrainian war indicate how conflict feeds hunger, ostracizing people out of their homes and erasing their sources of income entirely. Such conflicts inflict extreme conditions on civilians and survival becomes challenging.</p> <p>The ongoing climate change crisis is also another source of the rapid decline in the world’s current food supply. Natural events like droughts, greater CO2 concentrations in the atmosphere, floods, hotter temperatures, and water scarcity affect crops around the world. For example, corn and wheat production has declined rapidly in recent years due to extreme weather events, plant diseases, and a global water crisis. Poverty-stricken countries like Africa and India contain most of the world’s arable farmland, but if natural disasters continue occurring frequently, the incredible effort put in by farmers in plowing their acres of farmland will be in vain. Furthermore, unpredictable harvests aren’t within the control of farmers — they can only do so much in a day. According to the Food and Agriculture Organization, 80% of the causes behind an unpredictable harvest for crops in areas like Africa’s Sahel fall down to climate variability. In other areas of the world like Bangladesh and Vietnam, increasing sea levels create a different threat to food security. In such areas, coastal farmlands are frequently flooded by saltwater, which kills off rice crops. With half of Vietnam’s national rice production centered in the Mekong Delta (i.e., imagine roughly the size of Maryland), even a minor flood can have major consequences to wreck the country’s agricultural output. As one might naturally expect, given the unpredictable nature of natural disasters, climate change can also increase food wastage.</p> <p>The amount of food wastage is also another huge concern. In fact, some people argue that the rate of food production today isn’t the problem behind growing starvation numbers — rather, it’s the amount of food wastage. Just take our dining halls as an example. There’s so much food wastage that they have to flash figures on the amount of daily food wastage above the dustbins. On a global level though, roughly 17% of total global food production (or 1.3 million tons) is wasted on an annual basis. People are encouraged to take small portion sizes and take full advantage of leftovers, so anything left can be frozen (to avoid spoiling, of course) or added as an ingredient to another dish. While most people subconsciously know that their uneaten food could have gone to a poor family in a poverty-stricken country in the world, most people waste it anyways. They’re not at fault, for we have an improper system. Though some exist, we don’t have as many nets or organizations in the world to facilitate the process of sending uneaten food to starving families. Logically speaking, it makes sense why we haven’t made much progress towards achieving this goal because most food items are perishable. Nevertheless, we will need to figure out a workaround in the near future. Understanding food labeling is also another important idea, specifically the difference between “use by” and “best before.” “Use by” indicates the date up to which food is safe to be eaten, while ‘best before’ signifies that the food’s quality is best prior to that date, although it is still safe to be eaten afterwards in most cases.</p> <p>As the human population is likely to continue increasing rapidly, it becomes ever important to unlock new ways to accelerate food production and encourage people not to waste food meaninglessly. Any excess food can also be donated through in-person donations to food banks or beneficial mobile apps like Olio. There are multiple ways we can reduce our food waste print, yet some choose to actively ignore these suggestions (as indicated by the growing food wastage figure). Each little step can make a gradual impact on significantly reducing starvation issues in our world to ensure every person, regardless of financial conditions, receives a proper meal.</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="global-hunger"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How do volcanoes make lightning?</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/volcanoes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do volcanoes make lightning?"/><published>2023-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/volcanoes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/volcanoes/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>When hot, molten rock rises through the Earth’s crust and exits through to the surface, it often results in a volcanic eruption. These eruptions expel a large amount of ash, dust, rock, volatile gases, and lava relatively quickly. While we might think of these as the major features of a volcano, there’s often a magnificent visual sight that accompanies them: volcanic lightning. Even though every volcanic eruption will not be followed by a spectacular light show, it’s been observed many times.</p> <p>Volcanic lightning is a phenomenon that typically occurs at the initial stages of a volcanic eruption. Many scientists are puzzled by its exact cause. It can either happen close to the ground in dense ash clouds or high up near the stratosphere in the plume (a cylinder-shaped column) of volcanic smoke. For volcanic lightning that occurs near the surface, studies have attributed the cause to the friction produced by the rubbing of individual ash particles, generating sufficient static electricity to create a lightning bolt. On the other hand, sky-high volcanic lightning has a more interesting cause — ice. Researchers speculate that as the plume of ash and water vapor rises from the volcano, ice begins to form in its highest layers. From there, lightning forms the same way it does in a thundercloud, where collisions of ice crystals generate sufficient electric charge to spark a lightning strike.</p> <p>This strange formation of lightning has been observed around a number of recent volcanic eruptions, including Iceland’s Eyjafjallajökull, Japan’s Sakurajima, Italy’s Mt. Etna, and Chile’s Puyehue, Calbuco and Chaiten volcanoes. Interestingly, this phenomenon was not only captured during Mt. Vesuvius’ last eruption in 1944 but was accurately described nearly two thousand years ago when it actually erupted centuries ago!</p> <p>Each lightning strike is the exchange of roughly 1020 electrons, or if you want to see the number of zeros, 100,000,000,000,000,000,000 charged particles. Many mistakenly believe atoms as being neutral, with an equal number of protons and electrons. However, heat and friction make it surprisingly easy for atoms to gain or lose electrons by breaking bonds, transforming them into ions. Given the temperature of volcanoes, it’s an energetically favorable reaction for an atom to become ionized, where it either gains or loses an electron(s). If these ions can be separated from one another, a separation of charge forms, which creates a voltage. When the difference in voltage between two regions becomes too great, it spontaneously becomes conductive and creates a decomposition of the material between these regions. What follows is an exchange of charge that happens incredibly quickly, and that’s what you see as a lightning strike!</p> <p>As complicated as this phenomena might appear to be at first, there are really only three steps you need to make it happen: (1) start with an excess of cations and anions, (2) separate them, and (3) see lightning happen due to the voltage difference!</p> <hr/> <p>“Volcanic Lightning Happens at the Beginning of a Volcanic Eruption.” <i>Discovery</i>, https://www.discovery.com/science/volcanic-lightning-happens-at-the-beginning-of-a-volcanic-erupti.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/volcanoes-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/volcanoes-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/volcanoes-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/volcanoes.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural-phenomena"/><category term="volcanoes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Current View of the Ongoing Impacts of the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/covid19-impacts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Current View of the Ongoing Impacts of the COVID-19 Pandemic"/><published>2023-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/covid19-impacts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/covid19-impacts/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Towards late 2019 and early 2020, the coronavirus disease spread rampant across the world and drastically transformed most aspects of daily life. It changed the way we communicate, care for others, educate our children, work, and so much more! Over the past few years, the world has indeed seen a permanent shift in various forms of life, the economy, medicine, and beyond due to the pandemic.</p> <p>For one thing, some increasingly turned towards using video-calling platforms such as Google Meets and Zoom to combat loneliness and social isolation. Recent research studies suggest that many such platforms have design flaws that exhaust the human mind and body. Terming this condition as “Zoom burnout,” experts have taken the medium apart and assessed its individual technical aspects, identifying a few causes behind exhaustion in prolonged video chats. As one cause, spending hours resolving technical bugs like sound issues, glitches, and screen freezes can disrupt our ability to interpret messages and add to our unease, leading to increased mental strain and exhaustion. Additionally, in-person meetings and audio phone conversations allow one to walk around and move wherever they please, but with videoconferencing calls, many desktop computer cameras have a fixed field of view, meaning one has to remain in the same position for the entirety of the conversation: sitting at a desk and staring at a computer screen for hours can naturally take a heavy toll on our well-being and, consequently, lead researchers to believe less mobility and physical activity as one of the biggest reasons for increased fatigue. Nonverbal communications like waving to a friend or indicating how many apples you want by holding up three fingers are interpreted subconsciously in face-to-face meetings, but it’s not as obvious to interpret in a video call setting — more mental processing is required to understand the message. Understanding nonverbal cues and gestures like facial expressions, voice pitch or tone, and body language are harder to process online. According to Stanford University researcher <a href="https://news.stanford.edu/2021/02/23/four-causes-zoom-fatigue-solutions/">Jeremy Bailenson</a>, “If you want to show someone that you are agreeing with them, you have to do an exaggerated nod or put your thumbs up. That adds cognitive load as you’re using mental calories in order to communicate.”</p> <p>This pandemic was the first pandemic in which online resources and social media were used extensively to push forward policies and keep people connected, informed, productive, and, most importantly, safe. At the same time, however, the technology we rely on is enabling and amplifying an infodemic that undermined the global response and threatened measures to control the pandemic. Misinformation costs lives, for without the honest dissemination of information, diagnostic tests went unused, vaccine promotion campaigns did not meet their targets, and the virus continued to thrive. Already suffering from mental health issues because of social isolation, people have reported feeling worse due to confusion, conflict, and conspiracy theories spreading quickly in the news media and online. Experts from Stanford University have developed a machine learning model to track the spread of misinformation in social media. The program relies on using individuals’ “susceptibility” to false information as an initial score and their likeliness to spread it to others. They discovered that older adults, youths (especially those highly active on social media), and those with minimal years of educational background seemed to be the most prone to falling for false information. Individuals at political extremes are also more likely to believe information that confirms pre-existing biases. This effect is of particular concern when the information comes from a well-trusted source. Indeed, preventing the spread of misinformation is largely a challenge, especially with the advances in modern technological capabilities. However, in the meantime, it’s important that we consider making progress now towards alleviating its power to twist some of our minds.</p> <p>Right now, we’re at the precipice of a new technological age that will have amplifying effects in the following decades. Using novel CRISPR technology, genetic engineering can enable researchers to program biology. This technology powers the very vaccines that have been used to inoculate the world from COVID-19. Researchers have developed a vaccine in record time—a source of inspiration for them to create vaccines for other diseases faster. Momentum behind this technology will push research into resolving new diseases and enabling superhuman capabilities. In fact, experts are currently exploring ways to fight cancer by using the messenger RNA (mRNA) technology within the COVID-19 vaccine: mRNA can stimulate the body’s immune system to identify cancer cells and attack them. See <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/news-events/cancer-currents-blog/2022/mrna-vaccines-to-treat-cancer">this link</a> for more information.</p> <p>In the following year, the US and other countries will hopefully realize that working together will help solve problems that are on a global scale. Through seeing the origin and spread of the Delta variant in India or the Omicron variant in South Africa, countries will realize that this is a global problem, not an Indian or African problem. Past events like the Atlanta spa shootings in March 2021 show how inequality and violence will likely increase against East Asians, for people who have lost their loved ones will direct their frustration towards them; in fact, recent studies show that Americans rate East Asians lower in multiple characteristics than otherwise identical East Asian Americans. However, people need to let bygones be bygones since more violence will only breed more violence. Employers will institute more remote-working policies for productivity gains. We will also see more economic safety nets put in place like the COVID stimulus package so that citizens will be less stressed and have more support through their financial hardships.</p> <p>At a first glance, it may seem as if people will remember how the pandemic caused an alarming number of deaths (6.3 million worldwide), a global recession, and other negative impacts. However, that is not the case — the pandemic has reshaped the world, making us aware of ideas never considered before and the faults within our own system. This should ultimately be a lesson for us.</p> <hr/> <p>“Coronavirus Disease 2019 (Covid-19).” <i>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</i>, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 19 Dec. 2022, https://www.cdc.gov/dotw/covid-19/index.html.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/covid19-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/covid19-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/covid19-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/covid19-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="covid19"/><category term="covid19-impacts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moonbows: What’s a lunar rainbow?</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/moonbows/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moonbows: What’s a lunar rainbow?"/><published>2023-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/moonbows</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/moonbows/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>In the late 1700s, English poet William Cole put his description of a moonbow into verse:</p> <i>The atmosphere with humid vapors flow / And the Moon displays her lunar bow.</i> <p>Scientifically speaking though, moonbows, also known as “lunar rainbows,” occur when moonlight shines on water droplets. As the light passes through the droplet, it refracts off the back of the droplet and exits the droplet after bending a second time. This bending of light causes it to split into its individual color wavelengths of red, orange, yellow, green, blue, indigo, and violet.</p> <p>But moonbows are more rare than rainbows — this phenomenon occurs only when the Moon is very low (for nerds, no more than 42 degrees above the horizon), the sky is dark, and the rain is falling opposite the moon. As displayed by the image above, they usually look spooky-white rather than the famous, well-known set of rainbow colors. Fascinatingly, all of the colors of the spectrum are actually present in a moonbow; however, because moonlight is far less intense than sunlight, the naked eye has can’t detect these various colors in the moonlight, meaning we see more of a “white” rainbow per se (i.e., white being the combination of all of light’s visible colors). (If you’re a photographer, however, the colors of a moonbow will show up in long exposures or on high-speed film.) The size of a moonbow depends on the moon’s height in the sky: the lower the moon, the bigger the moonbow. Typically, the largest moonbows occur when the Moon is within only an hour of rising or setting and is at its brightest and fullest.</p> <p>Generally, one will always spot a moonbow near a waterfall, creating a thin layer of mist and making the sighting of a moonbow possible. One of the most revered places to witness a moonbow is the Victoria Falls in Zimbabwe. One can enter via the Zambian or the Zimbabwean rain forest during a full moon. Every time during the full Moon, the rainforest opens its doors for a special tour during the evening for travellers to witness the moonbow. Niagara Falls also was once home to this unique phenomenon, but now due to development of the surrounding areas, it has created light pollution and moonbows are no longer visible there anymore. There are other places also where one can witness this phenomenon, including the Wallaman Falls in Australia, the Yosemite Falls in California, the Kihei Falls in Hawaii, and amidst other places. And the best time to witness the phenomenon is during the months of June, July and August.</p> <p>Lunar halos are other circles of light around the Moon. But don’t be mistaken — moonbows and lunar halos aren’t the same thing! While halos are also created when moonlight refracts off of water droplets in the atmosphere, this water is in the form of frozen ice crystals in cirrus clouds, not liquid droplets. Another difference between the two is that a halo creates a ring around the Moon while the center of a moonbow’s arc appears in the direction opposite of the Moon.</p> <hr/> <p>Grovier, Kelly. “The Rare Phenomenon of the ‘Moonbow’.” <i>BBC Culture</i>, BBC, 24 Feb. 2022, https://www.bbc.com/culture/article/20161021-the-rare-phenomenon-of-the-moonbow.</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/moonbows-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/moonbows-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/moonbows-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/moonbows.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural-phenomena"/><category term="moonbows"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finalizing Blog Topic</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/finalizing-blog-topic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finalizing Blog Topic"/><published>2023-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/finalizing-blog-topic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/finalizing-blog-topic/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>For this semester, I plan on writing my Passion blogs on surreal natural phenomena that occur in the world (e.g., moonbows, shooting stars, whirlpools, etc.). As for my Civic Issues blog, I plan on writing about starvation concerns and global hunger in today’s society. I look forward to getting started next week!</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="other"/><category term="global-hunger"/><category term="natural-phenomena"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Blog Transition</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/new-blog-transition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Blog Transition"/><published>2023-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/new-blog-transition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2023/new-blog-transition/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>With regards to my “This I Believe” podcast, I was hoping to either write about how there is no substitute for effort/hard work or how to find a home for oneself. As for my Passion Blog, I was torn between either continuing writing about my obsession with puzzles from last semester or writing about surreal natural phenomena that occur in the world (e.g., shooting stars, whirlpools, etc.). I will most probably go with the latter. As for my Civic Issues Blog, I was contemplating on writing about prevalent issues like climate action or starvation concerns, especially in developing countries.</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="other"/><category term="climate-change"/><category term="global-hunger"/><category term="puzzles"/><category term="natural-phenomena"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Post COVID-19 Pandemic: A Reflection of the Current State of the World</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/covid19-reflection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post COVID-19 Pandemic: A Reflection of the Current State of the World"/><published>2022-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/covid19-reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/covid19-reflection/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Ever since the pandemic broke out in December 2019, it has increased individualism among us. The pandemic has changed the nature of our “typical” social interactions; we don’t interact with other people in-person as much anymore. Many of us would agree that video calling can be a nicer way of chatting with others because it lets us physically see and speak to anyone regardless of where they are in the world, which was especially true with the rise in loneliness during the pandemic. As Zoom dominated — and continues to dominate — the video-calling industry, we shift to it as our main form of communication with others: in-person meetings are closer to becoming obsolete essentially, as video-calling becomes the new trend in today’s developing world. And even work life, too! Take the technology industry as an example. Company leaders have witnessed a significant boost in work output as they allow their employees to work from home on a few days in the weeks, and, consequently, some have implemented hybrid-working policies.</p> <p>There have been studies that show more than 90% of data generated in the world have been in the last few years. Almost every year, there are new advances in artificial intelligence (AI) like OpenAI’s language model that uses deep learning to produce human-like text, alarmingly indistinguishable deep-fake videos and images, or DeepMind’s AlphaFold AIbased algorithm that solved a 50-year old challenge in proteomics. Therefore, I have no doubt that this field will continue to grow in the coming decades. However, at the same time, the evolution of technology goes to make sure that tasks that humans could do earlier can now be achieved by machines and technology, therefore creating a shortage of jobs. And even more concerning, a rise in technology has created a dependence on our devices, tools, and processes. There’s not a requirement to think or recall information because everything is instantly available to us in a giant database, the Internet. Even a little tool, like a calculator, reduces the necessity to perform mental calculations or skills to try to do mathematics because you’ll solve equations by crunching them into the device that “magically” spits out answers/numbers. With regards to the recent COVID-19 pandemic, it caused an inevitable surge in the use of digital technologies due to the social distancing norms and nationwide lockdowns instituted in place; as such, video-conferencing platforms like Zoom were on the rise to build and maintain relationships. This embodies the commonplace of reliance on technology, as people become more reliant and overuse technology to the point where it’s unnecessary — some people are video calling their neighbors who live two minutes away from them!</p> <p>Homeschooling was also on the rise with the outbreak of the pandemic. As schools were not able to provide ideal in-person instruction anymore, young children were less likely to attend Zoom lecture videos and, consequently, were not able to easily grasp concepts and fundamental ideas. Furthermore, older students like high school students and college students took advantage of the situation and, quite frankly, cheated on examinations. Essentially, the pandemic has taught us that online instruction is an unfavorable form of instruction that shouldn’t be repeated again in the future, unless absolutely necessary because of the circumstances. This embodies the commonplace of in-person instruction reigning as the most efficient form of teaching, not online instruction.</p> <p>With the pandemic’s brutal waves, the US and other countries will hopefully realize in the following years that working together will help solve problems that are on a global scale. Through seeing the spread of the COVID-19 variants in the US, countries will realize that this is a global problem, not a US problem. In the coming years, we will also hopefully see more economic safety nets put in place like the COVID stimulus package that the citizens will be less stressed, more supportive, and inclusive of their communities — that’s the long-term goal!</p> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/covid19-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/covid19-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/covid19-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/covid19-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/covid19-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/covid19-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/covid19-2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/covid19-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="covid19"/><category term="reflection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ideas for History of a Public Controversy Project</title><link href="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/history-of-a-controversy-project-ideas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ideas for History of a Public Controversy Project"/><published>2022-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/history-of-a-controversy-project-ideas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asen4.github.io/blog/2022/history-of-a-controversy-project-ideas/"><![CDATA[<div> <p>Gun violence has been a highly-debated topic in the country for the last several years. At a time, it seemed like there was either a mass shooting or other act of gun violence everyday, although the situation has normalized in the past few months. While some gun control advocates uphold and support the Second Amendment, others feel they are a harm towards our safety at large.</p> <p>Maybe we could also consider doing something on universal healthcare. While universal healthcare already exists in countries like Sweden, Hong Kong, and Kuwait, where the local and federal government pays for most costs associated with healthcare coverage, there has been widespread disagreement over how to control high insurance costs, bureaucratic treatment obstacles, and deep socioeconomic inequalities.</p> <p>The Russian-Ukrainian conflict could also be considered another option. Was it ethical? We would, of course, have to examine the relationships between Russia and Ukraine over history, delving more into the issue from the perspective of both sides.</p> <p>We could also consider the climate change crisis. Is global warming real? Is it caused mainly by human activity? How harmful is it likely to be? What can we do about it? Some skeptics argue that the dangers of climate change are exaggerated, while others accept global warming as real but dismiss evidence that suggests it’s connected to human activity. Government regulation, suppression of scientific data for political gain, and international agreements on climate change often play a role in the debate.</p> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="civic-issues"/><category term="history-of-a-public-controversy-project"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>